Ante-Nicene Fathers, Vol VII: Lactantius: The Phœnix

Ante-Nicene Fathers, Vol VII:
Lactantius: The Phœnix

Early Church Fathers  Index

p. 324

The Phœnix

By an Uncertain Author. Attributed to Lactantius  2011

There is a happy spot, retired 2012 in the first East, where the great gate of the eternal pole lies open. It is not, however, situated near to his rising in summer or in winter, but where the sun pours the day from his vernal chariot. There a plain spreads its open tracts; nor does any mound rise, nor hollow valley open 2013 itself. But through twice six ells that place rises above the mountains, whose tops are thought to be lofty among us. Here is the grove of the sun; a wood stands planted with many a tree, blooming with the honour of perpetual foliage. When the pole had blazed with the fires of Phaethon, that place was uninjured by the flames; and when the deluge had immersed the world in waves, it rose above the waters of Deucalion. No enfeebling diseases, no sickly old age, nor cruel death, nor harsh fear, approaches hither, nor dreadful crime, nor mad desire of riches, nor Mars, nor fury, burning with the love of slaughter. 2014 Bitter grief is absent, and want clothed in rags, and sleepless cares, and violent hunger. No tempest rages there, nor dreadful violence of the wind; nor does the hoar-frost cover the earth with cold dew. No cloud extends its fleecy 2015 covering above the plains, nor does the turbid moisture of water fall from on high; but there is a fountain in the middle, which they call by the name of “living;” 2016 it is clear, gentle, and abounding with sweet waters, which, bursting forth once during the space of each 2017 month, twelve times irrigates all the grove with waters. Here a species of tree, rising with lofty stem, bears mellow fruits not about to fall on the ground. This grove, these woods, a single 2018 bird, the phœnix, inhabits,—single, but it lives reproduced by its own death. It obeys and submits 2019 to Phœbus, a remarkable attendant. Its parent nature has given it to possess this office. When at its first rising the saffron morn grows red, when it puts to flight the stars with its rosy light, thrice and four times she plunges her body into the sacred waves, thrice and four times she sips water from the living stream. 2020 She is raised aloft, and takes her seat on the highest top of the lofty tree, which alone looks down upon the whole grove; and turning herself to the fresh risings of the nascent Phœbus, she awaits his rays and rising beam. And when the sun has thrown back the threshold of the shining gate, and the light gleam 2021 of the first light has shone forth, she begins to pour strains of sacred song, and to hail 2022 the new light with wondrous voice, which neither the notes of the nightingale 2023 nor the flute of the Muses can equal with Cyrrhæan 2024 strains. But neither is it thought that the dying swan can imitate it, nor the tuneful strings of the lyre of Mercury. After that Phœbus has brought back his horses to the open heaven, 2025 and continually advancing, has displayed 2026 his whole orb; she applauds with thrice-repeated flapping of her wings, and having thrice adored the fire-bearing head, is silent. And she also distinguishes the swift hours by sounds not liable to error by day and night: an overseer 2027 of the groves, a venerable priestess of the wood, and alone admitted to thy secrets, O Phœbus. And when she has p. 325 now accomplished the thousand years of her life, and length of days has rendered her burdensome, 2028 in order that she may renew the age which has glided by, the fates pressing 2029 her, she flees from the beloved couch of the accustomed grove. And when she has left the sacred places, through a desire of being born 2030 again, then she seeks this world, where death reigns. Full of years, she directs her swift flight into Syria, to which Venus herself has given the name of Phœnice; 2031 and through trackless deserts she seeks the retired groves in the place, where a remote wood lies concealed through the glens. Then she chooses a lofty palm, with top reaching to the heavens, which has the pleasing 2032 name of phœnix from the bird, and where 2033 no hurtful living creature can break through, or slimy serpent, or any bird of prey. Then Æolas shuts in the winds in hanging caverns, lest they should injure the bright 2034 air with their blasts, or lest a cloud collected by the south wind through the empty sky should remove the rays of the sun, and be a hindrance 2035 to the bird. Afterwards she builds for herself either a nest or a tomb, for she perishes that she may live; yet she produces herself. Hence she collects juices and odours, which the Assyrian gathers from the rich wood, which the wealthy Arabian gathers; which either the Pygmæan 2036 nations, or India crops, or the Sabæan land produces from its soft bosom. Hence she heaps together cinnamon and the odour of the far-scented amomum, and balsams with mixed leaves. Neither the twig of the mild cassia nor of the fragrant acanthus is absent, nor the tears and rich drop of frankincense. To these she adds tender ears 2037 of flourishing spikenard, and joins the too pleasing pastures 2038 of myrrh. Immediately she places her body about to be changed on the strewed nest, and her quiet limbs on such 2039 a couch. Then with her mouth she scatters juices around and upon her limbs, about to die with her own funeral rites. Then amidst various odours she yields up 2040 her life, nor fears the faith of so great a deposit. In the meantime her body, destroyed by death, which proves the source of life, 2041 is hot, and the heat itself produces a flame; and it conceives fire afar off from the light of heaven: it blazes, and is dissolved into burnt ashes. And these ashes collected in death it fuses, 2042 as it were, into a mass, and has an effect 2043 resembling seed. From this an animal is said to arise without limbs, but the worm is said to be of a milky colour. And it suddenly increases vastly with an imperfectly formed 2044 body, and collects itself into the appearance of a well-rounded egg. After this it is formed again, such as its figure was before, and the phœnix, having burst her shell, 2045 shoots forth, even as caterpillars 2046 in the fields, when they are fastened by a thread to a stone, are wont to be changed into a butterfly. No food is appointed for her in our world, nor does any one make it his business to feed her while unfledged. She sips the delicate 2047 ambrosial dews of heavenly nectar which have fallen from the star-bearing pole. She gathers these; with these the bird is nourished in the midst of odours, until she bears a natural form. But when she begins to flourish with early youth, she flies forth now about to return to her native abode. Previously, however, she encloses in an ointment of balsam, and in myrrh and dissolved 2048 frankincense, all the remains of her own body, and the bones or ashes, and relics 2049 of herself, and with pious mouth brings it into a round form, 2050 and carrying this with her feet, she goes to the rising of the sun, and tarrying at the altar, she draws it forth in the sacred temple. She shows and presents herself an object of admiration to the beholder; such great beauty is there, such great honour abounds. In the first place, her colour is like the brilliancy 2051 of that which the seeds of the pomegranate when ripe take under the smooth rind; 2052 such colour as is contained in the leaves which the poppy produces in the fields, when Flora spreads her garments beneath the blushing sky. Her shoulders and beautiful breasts shine with this covering; with this her head, with this her neck, and the upper parts of her back shine. And her tail is extended, varied with yellow metal, in the spots of which mingled purple blushes. Between her wings there is a bright 2053 mark above, as 2054 Tris on high is wont to paint a cloud from above. She gleams resplendent with a mingling of the green emerald, and a shining beak 2055 of pure horn opens itself. Her eyes are large; 2056 you might p. 326 believe that they were two jacinths; 2057 from the middle of which a bright flame shines. An irradiated crown is fitted 2058 to the whole of her head, resembling on high the glory of the head of Phœbus. 2059 Scales cover her thighs spangled with yellow metal, but a rosy 2060 colour paints her claws with honour. Her form is seen to blend the figure of the peacock with that of the painted bird of Phasis. 2061 The winged creature which is produced in the lands of the Arabians, whether it be beast or bird, can scarcely equal her magnitude. 2062 She is not, however, slow, as birds which through the greatness of their body have sluggish motions, and a very heavy 2063 weight. But she is light and swift, full of royal beauty. Such she always shows herself 2064 in the sight of men. Egypt comes hither to such a wondrous 2065 sight, and the exulting crowd salutes the rare bird. Immediately they carve her image on the consecrated marble, and mark both the occurrence and the day with a new title. Birds of every kind assemble together; none is mindful of prey, none of fear. Attended by a chorus of birds, she flies through the heaven, and a crowd accompanies her, exulting in the pious duty. But when she has arrived at the regions of pure ether, she presently returns; 2066 afterwards she is concealed in her own regions. But oh, bird of happy lot and fate, 2067 to whom the god himself granted to be born from herself! Whether it be female, or male, or neither, or both, happy she, who enters into 2068 no compacts of Venus. Death is Venus to her; her only pleasure is in death: that she may be born, she desires previously to die. She is an offspring to herself, her own father and heir, her own nurse, and always a foster-child to herself. She is herself indeed, but not the same, since she is herself, and not herself, having gained eternal life by the blessing of death. p. 327

Footnotes

324:2011

[A curious expansion of the fable so long supposed to be authentic history of a natural wonder, and probably derived from Oriental tales corroborated by travellers. See vol. i. p. 12; also iii. 554. Yezeedee bird-worship may have sprung out of it.]

324:2012

Remotus. The reference is supposed to be to Arabia, though some think that India is pointed out as the abode of the phœnix.

324:2013

Hiat.

324:2014

Cædis amore furor. There is another reading, “cedit.”

324:2015

Vellera, “thin fleecy clouds.” So Virg., Georg., i. 397; Tenuia nec lanæ per cœlum vellera ferri.

324:2016

Vivum.

324:2017

Per singula tempora mensum.

324:2018

Unica, “the only one.” It was supposed that only one phœnix lived at one time. So the proverb “Phœnice rarior.”

324:2019

Birds were considered sacred to peculiar gods: thus the phœnix was held sacred to Phœbus. [Layard, Nineveh, vol. ii. p. 462.]

324:2020

Gurgite.

324:2021

Aura. So Virg., Æneid, vi. 204: “Discolor unde auri per ramos aura refulsit.”

324:2022

Ciere.

324:2023

Aëdoniæ voces. The common reading is “Ædoniæ,” contrary to the metre.

324:2024

i.e., strains of Apollo and the Muses, for Cyrrha is at the foot of Parnassus, their favourite haunt.

324:2025

Aperta Olympi, when he has mounted above the horizon.

324:2026

Protulit.

324:2027

Antistes.

325:2028

Gravem, i.e., a burden to herself.

325:2029

Fatis urgentibus; others read “spatiis vergentibus.”

325:2030

Studio renascendi.

325:2031

Venus was worshipped in Syro-Phœnice.

325:2032

Gratum; others read “Graium,” Grecian.

325:2033

Quà; another reading is “quam,” that which.

325:2034

Purpureum. There may be a reference to the early dawn.

325:2035

Obsit.

325:2036

Some ancient writers place these fabulous people in India, others beyond Arabia.

325:2037

Aristas. The word is sometimes applied, as here, to spikenard.

325:2038

Et sociat myrrhæ pascua grata nimis; another reading is, “et sociam myrrhæ vim, Panachaia tuæ.”

325:2039

In talique toro; others, “vitalique toro,” i.e., on a death-bed.

325:2040

Commendat.

325:2041

Genitali, “productive;” observe the antithesis.

325:2042

Conflat.

325:2043

Effectum; others read, “ad fœtum seminis instar habent.”

325:2044

Cum corpore curto; others read, “cum tempore certo.”

325:2045

Ruptis exuviis. The same word is used by Virgil to describe the serpent slipping its skin—“positis exuviis.”

325:2046

Tineæ.

325:2047

Tenues; others read “teneri.”

325:2048

Thure soluto.

325:2049

Exuvias suas.

325:2050

In formam conglobat.

325:2051

Quem croceum. The word is properly used to denote the colour of saffron; it is also applied to other bright colours.

325:2052

Sub cortice lævi; the common reading is “sub sidere cæli.”

325:2053

Clarum insigne; others read, “aurum…insigneque.”

325:2054

Ceu; others read, “seu.”

325:2055

Gemmea cuspis. Her beak is of horn, but bright and transparent as a gem.

325:2056

Ingentes oculi; others read, “oculos.”

326:2057

Hyacinthos; gems of this colour.

326:2058

Æquatur.

326:2059

i.e., the rays of the sun.

326:2060

Roseus; others read, “roseo honore.”

326:2061

The pheasant.

326:2062

Magniciem. Some take this as denoting the name of a bird, but no such bird is known.

326:2063

Pergrave pondus; others read, “per grave pondus,” by reason of the heavy weight.

326:2064

Se exhibet; others read “se probat.”

326:2065

Tanti ad miracula visus. [Deut. iv. 17.]

326:2066

Inde; others read, “ille,” but the allusion is very obscure.

326:2067

Fili, “the thread,” i.e. of fate.

326:2068

Colit. [Badger’s Nestorians, vol. i. p. 122.]

Next: A Poem on the Passion of the Lord